Finding Aid for Ralph Loomis Papers 1963-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph Loomis Papers 1963-1989, 1968-1975
Loomis, Ralph A., 1923-
6.5 linear feet
9835 Aa 2
Ralph A. Loomis was a professor of English in the English and Humanities department of the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan. He made significant contributions to faculty governance while teaching at the University of Michigan, 1953-1993. The collection ranges from 1963 to 1989 (bulk 1968-1975, 1983). The records contain information on the College of Engineering and the Department of English, including the dissolution of the Department and Loomis' involvement in many committees on campus, and documentation of the Johnathan Marwil court case.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Ralph A. Loomis in April 1997. Donor no. 8581
The collection is open for research except for scattered files as noted.
Ralph A. Loomis was a professor of English in the English and Humanities department of the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan. He taught at the university from 1953 until 1992.
Ralph A. Loomis was born August 22, 1923. He received degrees from the University of Missouri, Oberlin College and Northwestern University, receiving his doctorate from Northwestern in 1956. His career at Michigan was spent teaching English in the College of Engineering. In 1993, he became a Professor Emeritus of English with the College of Engineering. During his almost forty years at the university he was very active in departmental, college, and university committees. He was also involved in the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) during the same period of time. As a member of the AAUP he served on committees at the university, state, and national level, including six years as president of the Michigan Conference (state organization) of the AAUP.
As an active member of committees at both the University of Michigan and as a member of the AAUP, Ralph Loomis comprehensively collected correspondence and memoranda from the work of Department of English and Humanities committees, College of Engineering committees, and University committees established by the Senate Assembly and SACUA, as well as various ad hoc committees established by the university.
As a member of the AAUP, Ralph Loomis collected a wide array of correspondence, memoranda, and minutes of the university, state, and national chapters, as well as working committees of those chapters. Especially interesting is the collection of papers relating to collective bargaining. These papers include speeches that Ralph Loomis gave on collective bargaining, as well as papers relating to the collective bargaining elections at Eastern Michigan, Northern Michigan, and Wayne State, which occurred during 1971 to 1972.
The collection is divided into four major series: Department of Humanities/English, College of Engineering, University of Michigan, American Association of University Professors, Dissolving of the Department, General Files, and Johnathan Marwil Case.
Subjects:
Loomis, Ralph A., 1923-; Marwil, Jonathan, 1940-; American Association of University Professors. University of Michigan Chapter.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering. Dept. of English.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Department of Humanities/English
  The Department of Humanities/English of the College of Engineering series (Box 1) is arranged by the committees on which he served: the Ad Hoc Review Committee, the Administrative Committee, the Curriculum Committee. The committee folders cover primarily the period between 1965 to 1975.
  - Ad Hoc Review Committee, 3 folders
    - April 1970-May 1970 (Box 1)
    - June 1970-December 1970 (Box 1)
    - Report October 1970 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Committee, 4 folders
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Committee, 5 folders
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Department Newsnotes 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Staff Correspondence and Memoranda, 7 folders
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes 1972-1976 (Box 1)
- College of Engineering
  The College of Engineering of the University of Michigan series contains correspondence, memoranda, and minutes from primarily the Scholastic Standing Committee and the Library Council. The committee folders cover primarily 1971-1985.
  - Ad Hoc Review Committee
    - circa 1963 (Box 1)
    - circa March 1966 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Committee 1971 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes and Agendas
    - 1969-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Rules Committee circa 1974 (Box 1)
  - Library Committee, 2 folders
    - 1982-1986 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1972-1975 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Papers about Engineering Education (Box 2)
  - Nominating Committee 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - North Campus Move 1975 (Box 2)
  - Scholastic Standing Committee
    - 1971-1973 (Box 5)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2048 ]
    - 1974-1975 (Box 5)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2050 ]
    - 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - circa 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Staff Memoranda 1981-1984 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan general series contains correspondence and memoranda from Senate and SACUA committees, such as the Early Retirement Committee. The series covers primarily 1971 to 1978.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Annuitants Benefits 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Advise President Hatcher on the Relation of the University to the State Board of Education. 1964 (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Advise the Vice President on Allocation of Salary Adjustments 1973 (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee of University of Michigan Health Maintenance Organization 1975-1978 (Box 2)
  - Affirmative Action Committee 1975 (Box 2)
  - Association of Michigan Collegiate Faculties
    - Memoranda and Minutes 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Committee on the Economic Status of the Faculty
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 2 folders
      - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Early Retirement Subcommittee
      - Correspondence and Memoranda 1972-1973, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Report 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Retirees' Income Subcommittee
      - Correspondence and Memoranda 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Tenure 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, University of Michigan Chapter Board
    - Minutes and Correspondence 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Senate
    - Tenure Committee
      - Correspondence and Memoranda 1966-1971 (Box 2)
  - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs
    - Committee on Faculty Participation in Governance, University of Michigan-Flint 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 2 folders
      - circa 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - circa 1980s (Box 2)
    - Student Relations Subcommittee 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - University Club Board of Directors 1978 (Box 2)
  - University Library Council, Memoranda and Minutes, 3 folders
    - 1974-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
  - Vice-president Brinkerhoff's HMO Advisory Committee circa 1980 (Box 2)
- American Association of University Professors
  The Association of University Professors series contains correspondence, memoranda and minutes from the university chapter, the state chapter, and the national chapter. The series also contains a large amount of speeches, correspondence, and memoranda relating to collective bargaining campaigns at Michigan universities. The series covers primarily 1970 to 1979.
  - Assembly of State Conferences
    - Annual Meeting 1973 (Box 3)
    - Annual Meeting 1986 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1970-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Task Force Report 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Caucus of Midwestern Conferences 1972-1975 (Box 3)
  - Collective Bargaining
    - Bloomington, IN speech 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Eastern Michigan University 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Ferris State College, MI speech 1972 (Box 3)
    - Indianapolis, IN speech 1971 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 3)
    - Northern Michigan University 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Wayne State University 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Membership Kit 1984 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Conference
    - Adrian, MI, speech 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1964-1978, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Council, Minutes and Agendas 1963-1973, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Executive, Minutes and Agendas 1968-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Financial Reports 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Junior College Issues
      - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Agendas 1984 (Box 3)
    - "News from the Lansing Scene" 1975-1984 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters 1966-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan-Flint, speech 1972 (Box 3)
  - National
    - Annual Meeting
      - 1965 (Box 3)
      - 1966 (Box 3)
      - 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1970-1988, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Committee F correspondence and memoranda 1970-1973, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee and Council Minutes 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Legislative Alert/ Legislative News 1975, 1985 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Chapter
    - Chapter Meeting Minutes 1979-1986 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1972-1988, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1972-1988, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Tenure Issues Correspondence 1972-1977 (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's Report 1973-1985 (Box 4)
- Dissolving of Department
  The Dissolving of Department series includes committee reports, correspondence, and faculty responses to the dissolving of the Department of Humanities from the College of Engineering and its movement into the College of LSA. The bulk of the material is from 1983.
  - American Association of University Professors undated (Box 6)
  - Committees
    - Advisory Committee 1982-1983 (Box 6)
    - Executive Committee 1983 (Box 6)
    - Review Committee 1981-1983 (Box 6)
    - Senate Assembly Committee 1978, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
    - Transition Committee 1984 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - General 1983-1984 (Box 6)
    - Duderstadt, James 1981-1984 (Box 6)
    - Kuhn, William 1983 (Box 6)
    - Loomis, Ralph, From 1983 (Box 6)
    - Loomis, Ralph, To 1983 (Box 6)
    - Shapiro, Harold 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Department Manual (Box 6)
  - Department Review 1983 (Box 6)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1983 (Box 6)
  - Faculty Response
    - Gorman 1983 (Box 6)
    - Kaplan, Wilfred 1983 (Box 6)
    - Stevenson, Dwight 1983 (Box 6)
    - Zorach, Jonathan 1983 (Box 6)
  - Literature Stem 1983 (Box 6)
  - Memos 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1983 (Box 6)
  - Notes undated (Box 6)
  - Report on Unionization undated (Box 6)
  - Tenure Policy 1978-1979 (Box 6)
- General Files
  The General Files series is organized alphabetically by topical file. Of particular interest are: the file on the committees Loomis participated in, the promotions and awards he received, the water polo Flounders Group which he was a member of, fliers for radical movements that were occurring on campus, and notes on the speeches he presented. The series covers a broad range of material from 1962-1989.
  - American Association of University Professors 1962-1977 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Summer Festival 1980 (Box 6)
  - Awards and Promotions 1964-1987 (Box 6)
  - Center for Continuing Engineering Education 1965 (Box 6)
  - Committees 1975, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1963-1988 (Box 6)
  - Department of Population Planning 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - Financial Exigency 1971-1973 (Box 6)
  - Fleming Years undated (Box 6)
  - Flounders Group 1972-1988 (Box 6)
  - Health Maintenance Organization 1979, 1983, 1985 (Box 6)
  - LSA Deanship 1975 (Box 6)
  - Radical Movements 1966-1971 (Box 6)
  - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs 1964-1987 (Box 6)
  - Speeches undated (Box 6)
  - Student Affairs 1966, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Transfer to LSA 1984, 1989 (Box 6)
- Johnathan Marwil Case
  The Johnathan Marwil Case series contains information regarding the case and trial of faculty member Johnathan Marwil. Marwil was denied tenure and brought the issue to federal court. Loomis kept correspondence regarding the case, the opinions of the faculty on the issue, and copies of the information presented at the trial as well as a transcript of the trial. The material ranges from 1979-1980.
  - Committees
    - Administrative Committee 1977-1979 (Box 7)
    - Committee to Aid Marwil 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Executive Committee 1978 (Box 7)
    - Senate Advisory Review Committee (SARC) 1978 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Marwil, Johnathan, From 1977-1979 (Box 7)
    - Marwil, Jonathan, To 1976-1979 (Box 7)
    - Mathes, J.C. 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - Loomis, Ralph 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Senate Advisory Review Committee (SARC) 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Comments Against Marwil 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Comments Supporting Marwil 1977-1979 (Box 7)
  - Literature Position 1979 (Box 7)
  - Marwil Chronology undated (Box 7)
  - Memos 1978-1980 (Box 7)
  - Notes 1979 (Box 7)
  - Performance Review 1978 (Box 7)
  - Rhetoric Position 1978 (Box 7)
  - Rules for Faculty 1973-1974, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Student Evaluations 1973-1978, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Trial
    - Court Transcript 1980 (Box 7)
    - Loomis Statement 1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Preliminary 1979 (Box 7)
    - Public Documents 1980 (Box 7)
    - Result 1980 (Box 7)
    - Trial Brief 1980 (Box 7)
  - University Record 1979-1980 (Box 7)